VSDS Mahesh Akavarapu

 Popt. of CSE, IITK, Kanpur, U.P., India

 □ maheshak@cse.iitk.ac.in

in mahesh-akavarapu 😯 mahesh-ak

Research Interests

Computational Linguistics / Natural Language Processing, Historical Linguistics

As part of my PhD thesis, I worked on Axial Transformers and Graph-Attention-based architectures over the central problems in historical linguistics incorporating insights from Evolutionary Biology. Additionally, I worked on Phylogenetic testing of language families.

Education _____

PhD Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Computer Science July 2019 to present

- GPA: 3.84/4.00 (9.6/10.0)
- Advisor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Computer Science, Physics July 2014 to May 2019 BT (Second Major)

• GPA: 3.72/4.00 (9.3/10.0)

Awards / Honors _____

Prime Minister's Research Fellowship (2019-24): Grant of INR 200,000 per year (approx. USD 12,000 in total) from Ministry of Education, Government of India

Academic Excellence Award from IIT Kanpur (2015-16): Awarded to Top 10% students of the batch

Experience _____

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Research Fellow

Under Prime Minister's Research Fellowship

Kanpur, India Aug. 2019 to July 2024 4 years 11 months

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Student Researcher, Intern

• High Performance Computing in CUDA (Guide: Prof. Mahendra K. Verma)

Kanpur, India May 2018 to July 2018 2 months

Publications _____

A Likelihood Ratio Test of Genetic Relationship among Languages

June 2024

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Accepted to **NAACL 2024** (main), Mexico City, Mexico

Automated Cognate Detection as a Supervised Link Prediction Task with Cognate Transformer

Mar. 2024

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of EACL 2024, St. Julian's, Malta

Cognate Transformer for Automated Phonological Reconstruction and Cognate Reflex Prediction

Dec. 2023

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of EMNLP 2023, Singapore

Creation of a Digital Rig Vedic Index (Anukramani) for Computational Linguistic Tasks

Jan. 2023

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of World Sanskrit Conference 2023, Canberra, Australia

Invited Talks _____

- Evolutionary Biology-Inspired Language Models in Historical Linguistics, University of Tübingen (Online), Apr. 2024
- Tutorial on LLMs: Finetuning and Prompting, with Arnab Bhattacharya and Shubham K. Nigam, NIT Warangal (Online), Mar. 2024
- Tutorial on Legal Named Entity Recognition, with Shubham K. Nigam, NIT Trichy (Online), Dec. 2022

Teaching Assitance _____

- (CS 689) *Computational Linguistics for Indian Languages*, Instructor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya (Spring 2024, Fall 2022)
- (CS 63) Theory of Computation, Instructor: Dr. Raghunath Tewari (Fall 2023, 2022)
- (CS 315) *Principles of Database Systems*, Instructor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya (Spring 2023, Spring 2021)
- (CS 657) Information Retrieval, Instructor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya (Spring 2022)
- (CS 771) Introduction to Machine Learning, Instructor: Dr. Nisheeth Srivastava (Fall 2021)
- (CS 685) Data Mining, Instructor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya (Fall 2020)
- (ESC 101) *Fundamentals of Computing*, Instructor: Dr. Nisheeth Srivastava (Spring 2020), Dr. Piyush Rai (Fall 2019)

Technologies _____

Languages: Python, C/C++, HTML, Shell Scripting etc.

Libraries: PyTorch, TensorFlow, HuggingFace, Pandas etc.